for most of history the overwhelming
majority of the Earth's inhabitants have
owned more or less
nothing the clothes they stood up in
some bowls of pot in a pan
perhaps a broom and if things were going
really well a few farming implements
nations and peoples remained
consistently poor global gdp did not
grow at all from year-to-year the world
was in aggregate as hard up at 1,800 as
it had been at the beginning of time
however starting in the early 18th
century in the countries of North
Western Europe a remarkable phenomenon
occurred economies began to expand and
wages to rise families who've never
before have any money beyond what they
needed just to survive found they could
go shopping for small luxuries a comb or
a mirror a spare set of underwear a
pillow some thicker boots or a towel
their expenditure created a virtuous
economic cycle the more they spent the
more businesses grew the more wages rose
by the middle of the 18th century
observers recognize that they were
living through a period of apical change
that historians have since described as
the world first consumer revolution it
was in Britain where the changes were
most marked enormous new industry sprang
up to cater for the widespread demand
for goods that once been the preserve of
the very rich alone in England cities
you could buy furniture from chippendale
Hepplewhite and sheraton pottery from
which would and Darby cutlery from the
smithereens of sheffield and hats shoes
and dresses featured in the best selling
magazines like the gallery of fashion
and the ladies magazine styles for
clothes and hair which had formerly gone
unchanged for decades now altered every
year often extremely theatrical and
impractical directions in the early
1770s there was a craze for decorated
week so tall that tops could only be
accessed by standing on a chair
it was fun for the cartoonists so vivid
and numerous with the consumer novelties
that the austere dr. Johnson Riley
wondered whether prisoners were also
soon to be hanged
in a new way the Christian Church looked
on and did not approve up-and-down
England clergyman delivered bitter
sermons against the new materialism they
call it vanity which was a sin sons and
daughters were to be kept away from
shops God would not look kindly on those
who paid more attention to household
decoration than the state of their souls
but they're now emerged an intellectual
revolution that sharply altered the
understanding of the role of vanity in
an economy in 1723 a London physician
called burn at mandeville published an
economic trapped titled fable of the
bees which proposed that contrary to
centuries of religious and moral
thinking what made country's rich and
therefore safe honest generous spirit
and strong was a very minor on elevated
and apparently undignified activity
shopping for pleasure it was the
consumption of what mandeville called
fripperies hats bonnets gloves butter
dishes soup tureen shoehorns and hair
clips that provided the engine for
national prosperity and allow the
government to doing practice for the
church only knew how to sermonize about
in theory make a genuine difference to
the lives of the weak and the poor the
only way to generate wealth argued
mandeville was to ensure high demand for
absurd and unnecessary things of course
no one needed employed handbags silk
lined slippers or ice creams but it was
a blessing that they could be prompted
by fashion to want them for on the back
of demand for such trifles workshops
will be billed apprentices trained and
hospitals funded mandeville shocked his
audience with the starkness of the
choice he placed before them a nation
could either be very high-minded
spiritually elevated intellectually
refined and dirt poor or a slave to
luxury and idle consumption and very
rich Mandeville's dark thesis went on to
convince almost all the great Anglophone
economist and political thinkers of the
18th century there were nevertheless
some occasional departures from the new
economic orthodoxy one of the most
spirited and impassioned voices was that
of Switzerland greatest philosopher
jean-jacques Rousseau shocked by the
impact of the consumer revolution on the
manners and atmosphere of his name
Geneva he called for a return to a
simpler older way of life of the sort he
experienced in alpine villages or read
about in travelers accounts of the
native tribes of north america in the
remote corners of open cell or the vast
forests of Missouri there was blessedly
no concern for fashion and no one
upmanship around hair extensions Russo
recommended closing Geneva's borders and
imposing crippling taxes on luxury goods
so the people's energies could be
redirected towards non-material values
he looked back with fondness to the
austere martial spirit of Sparta
however even if research disagreed with
mandeville he did not seek to deny the
basic premise behind his analysis it
truly appear to be a choice between
decadent consumption and wealth on the
one hand and virtuous restrained and
poverty on the other it was simply that
Russo unusually preferred virtue to
wealth the parameters of this debate
have continued to dominate economic
thinking ever since weary encounter them
in ideological arguments between
capitalists and communists and free
marketeers and environmentalists but for
most of us the debate is no longer
pertinent we simply accept that we will
live in consumer economies with some
very unfortunate side effects to them
Chris advertising foodstuffs they're
unhealthy for us products that are
disconnected from any reasonable
assessment of our needs all this in
exchange for economic growth and high
employment we have chosen wealth over
virtue and irony Laden acceptance of
this dichotomy is what underpins the
approach of many pop artists in mid 20th
century America for example place
oldenburg developed a reputation for
taking modest consumer items many of
them food-related and reproducing them
enormous scale usually in outdoor
settings and vibrant polyester vinyl in
city squares one might once have
expected to find statues in honor of
political leaders or religious saints
won now came across outside hamburgers
giant cheesecakes huge fries decked with
ketchup or perhaps Oldenburg's most
famous work a 12 metre high stainless
steel inverted ice cream code oldenburg
vast versions of small things playfully
directed our attention to the peculiar
their dependence of modern economies on
the mass consumption of what are in
human terms some deeply negligible
products yet scale of Oldenburg's
objects was only superficially absurd
because it rather precisely reflected
their actual importance in our
collective economic Destiny's
nevertheless as oldenburg seem to
concede it was peculiar to be living in
a civilization founded on the back of
buns and sweetened tomorrow paste the
basis hinted at by the deflated d
tumescent appearance of many of the
giant burgers hotdogs and pizzas the one
question that's rarely been asked is
whether there might be a way to
attenuate a dispiriting choice to draw
on the best aspects of consumerism on
the one hand and high-mindedness on the
other without suffering there were sides
moral decadence and profound poverty
might be possible for a society to
develop that allows for consumer
spending and therefore provides
employment and welfare of a kind
directed at something other than
vanities and superfluities might be shot
for something other than nonsense
in other words might we have wealth and
a degree of virtue it is this
possibility of which we find some
intriguing hints in the work of Adam
Smith and eighteenth-century economist
too often read as a blunt apologist for
all aspects of consumerism but in fact
one of its more subtle and visionary
analysts in his book The Wealth of
Nations published in 1776 Adam Smith
seems at points willing to concede to
key aspects of Mandeville's argument
consumer societies do help the poor by
providing employment based around
satisfying what are often rather
sub-optimal purchases Smith was as ready
as other economist's to mock the
triviality of some consumer choices
while admiring their consequences all
those embroidered lace handkerchiefs
jewel snuff boxes and miniature temples
made of cream for dessert
they were flippant he conceded but they
encourage trade create employment and
generated immense wealth and would
therefore be firmly defended on this
score alone however Smith held out some
fascinating hopes for the future
he pointed out that consumption didn't
invariably have to involve the
trading of frivolous things he had seen
the expansion of the Edinburgh book
trade a new how larger market higher
education might become he understood how
much wealth was being accumulated
through the construction of Edinburgh is
extremely handsome and noble Newtown he
understood that humans have many higher
needs that require a lot of Labor
intelligence and work to fulfill but the
light outside of capitalist enterprise
has conceived off by realists like
burning mandeville among these are need
for education for self-understanding for
beautiful cities and for rewarding
social lives
the ultimate goal of capitalism and adam
smith's view was to tackle happiness in
all its complexities psychological and
not just merely material the capitalism
of our times still hasn't entirely come
around to resolving the awkward choices
that burn at mandeville and Jacques
Rousseau circled but the crucial hope
for the future is that we may not
forever need to be making money off
rather exploitive silly or vein consumer
appetites that we may also learn to
generate enormous profits from helping
people as consumers and producers in the
truly important and ambitious aspects of
their lives
the reform of capitalism hinges on an
odd sounding but critical task a new
kind of consumerism the conception of an
economy focused around buying and
selling services and goods focused on
our higher needs