I'm telling you it's like watching bambi learn how to walk
you're drunk mom and dad are gonna be bad maybe I'm a little drunk and those
crab cakes
did I not tell you to come straight to me with more crab cakes are ready i can
I settle
make love to you right here right now I really wish that you wouldn't
all you have to do it just get through a little bit more okay then we can put you
in bed and just smile and don't talk to anyone speeds let's hear from the
birthday girl huh beeps you see everybody's looking at me
the plans working I didn't even have to take off my top yet
hey Chandler you can't keep your hands off her for one second so i think its
nine
I think it's necessary
I i want to thank you all for coming
my family and my friends blue i really
like to say that time from you know
really like to say
that's right dad
cigarette
I got a box of did not getting my
underwear drawer is all ok it's ok
begins good i turn 30 today do anything
I want because I
ok quick help me get this off yeah