everyone so yeah like to thank all the
related shoulders that voted in favor of
the transaction in a pie overwhelming
margin so I think your faith will be
rewarded
it's really going to be adding some
amazing stuff like that comes out like I
just meeting with the earlier this
evening with the whole city injury team
and you know I don't have secret to this
yet but it's looking quite promising
that that a solar roof will actually
cost less than a normal roof before you
even take the value of electricity into
account
so the basic proposition would be would
you like a roof that looks better than
normal roof last twice as long cost less
and by the way generates electricity
required to get anything else maybe
there's a reason i'm not sure why but
it's looking actually looking really
promising and I think there's there's
even room for improvement be on there so
you know we're excited about what way
things are going to go with with the
solar roof integrated with the powerwall
and with the you know it's electric
electric cars so with that let's go to
questions
it's only questions I think should
appear on the screen or maybe not maybe
we'll have to read them or something
should be okay thanks
yeah okay so apparently there's new
political landscape and let's review
what you're referring to but yeah
something so the right one of the
biggest misunderstandings about Teslin
so somewhat counterintuitive is the
degree which is less reliance upon
incentives of subsidies the Bee
ironically if all incentives and
subsidies were removed for Tesla tells
us competitive position would increase
not decrease this is a like a really
fundamental misunderstanding we do
believe that should be incentives and
government centers for electric vehicles
but we believe that they should be there
for the good of the the industry and to
accelerate the advent of sustainable
transport not because Tesla needs them
and let me explain what I mean by this
the incentives either don't scale or
other disadvantaged just disadvantageous
if you take the zero-emission vehicle
credit where you get $5,000 it isn't
it's a nominal value of five thousand
dollars per credit and they say you
might get interested 22 of those per
vehicle or three so too would be worth
ten thousand dollars face value but
Tesla can only sell them to other car
companies for about fifty cents on the
dollar because the same mandate is is is
very weak we we only have fifty cents on
the dollar
however if General Motors or Ford
somebody else makes electric vehicle
that they get to monetize their credit
at a hundred cents on the dollar so if
they said two steps of credits per
vehicle generals would have a
five-thousand-dollar cost advantage over
Tesla that they do not what would happen
if they do have so if people are
concerned about ten incentives that
should be concerned well how did Tesla
overcome
the competitive disadvantage of TV
incentives not the other way around that
there's also the $75 federal tax credit
but that stops that accumulative quarter
million vehicles so it's essentially
irrelevant for any any high-volume
program as soon as we start making half
a million or million vehicles per year
that the term 50k cumulative or longer
have run out so no no state is most that
is impossible to scale electric vehicles
and have the incentive be relevant and
then ironically in California they put
an income cap on the 25-man develop an
incentive so many of our customers don't
even qualify for the between our all
incentive because of the income cap
which i think is really quite
destructive since really and doesn't
make any sense to me because we're the
only car company left in California like
has the biggest manufacturer in
California so I don't understand why
legislature with which would do such
thing that's ultimately to the detriment
of its own state integrate these things
puzzling and and then if you look at you
look internationally in in China which
is the world's biggest car market we
currently pay twenty-five cent import
duty and we have no access to incentives
because I car is not locally made that
the net effect is that our car costs
forty percent more than locally-made
vehicle so if we made the vehicle oakley
be before percent difference so normally
do not have access incentives we have a
huge penalty looking at other other
parts of the world Germany put a 60,000
your cap on the incentives conveniently
just below the Tesla in a contest in
Europe which the public yeah just look
it's actually very difficult rustic to
get can access any incentive Germany
Denmark the same thing Francis
considering doing the same thing so the
great irony is that if all the
incentives went 2-0
Chaz competitive position would
immediately improve like quite
significantly we don't think that's a
good thing for the world but it would be
a good thing for Tesla so i think that's
that's pretty important thing to
consider so I'm let's say the new
president did erase all incentives that
tells us competitive position would just
be better so that that's actually what
happened when the technology for the new
solar roof technology is well alter my
ass so hard to get
yeah this this was a almost entirely
developed by Tesla and solar city will
mostly by SolarCity some by Tesla and
then you know we may or may not use a
foam from 3m but the use of the format
particular application that we're
talking about was working or something
that we came up with but the court turn
ninety percent plus of the technology is
owned by a combined company
yeah so partially answered this question
so we expect to start doing the solar
roofs in volume percent summer next year
so what will enroll out that this four
main types if you saw the rollout and
we'll roll them out one at a time so
we'll start of probably like three month
intervals start with the one that
appears to be the most popular and then
and then roll the each new variant out
roughly on three-month cycles from
summer next year and that the cost will
obviously vary according to the size of
the house and the difficulties of the
installation but the important thing is
that the apples to apples comparison
compared to a regular roof are confident
we'll be at at least at and we believe
slightly below the cost of a regular
roof and then electricity is just a
bonus
well have to touch on this question with
a few times
we're trying to make an integrated
product you have an integrated solar
roof with the powerwall an electric car
I mean he's going to test the store just
say yes it just happens it all works its
seamless and you love it
thoughts on new competitors well it's
encouraging to see other comic is your
electric cars i am a little concerned
about the the pace and volume of what
they're doing since the seems to be
mostly aiming to just target whatever
the incentive threshold is and and then
not really too serious volume beyond
that so the as a moment ago the
incentives don't scale with volume so
the major manufacturers are not from
what we see maybe with the exception of
what folks walking says they're going to
do none of the competitors are planets
do serious volume in electric vehicles
yet that they're just sighs to stay
within the volume strains of the other
incentives so that the the like this
like this
the Chevrolet bolt the B is I think I'm
very for like 20 to 30,000 cars here but
really car like that should be three to
five hundred thousand per year for to
really make a difference
sure I understand this question
Oh model 3 we think we have military
from the beginning we said free charging
is not is not included in the in the
model 3 or not and if not free unlimited
charges that included of so free long
distance is but not free free local it's
just it becomes really unwieldy for
people to use the gas station approach
for electric cars like cars really
charge when you charge your phone but
then you just need some of the long
distance problem which is what the
supercharger stations will do
already answered all right and any and
it may take a few quick questions from
the audience
sure
the question is will each tile have a
solar cell behind it or will some not
and the answer is some will not but it's
important that they aesthetically look
the same so that you do not see a patchy
roof so it has to be aesthetically
consistent but it will not make sense to
put solar cells on every portion of the
roof because some portions are heavily
shaded as you point out
yeah just need to aesthetically
consistent today is not the time for the
announcement but I mean it's probably
yeah I don't know somewhere beginning of
spring or something like that
yeah yeah for four months from now I'm
sorry I just don't understand take like
maybe three or four more questions and
just over there
yes the question was what about the
incentives for for solar because there
is at currently thirty percent
investment tax credit all of the
efficiency with which that tax credit is
applied really diminish its its its true
value i think maybe fifteen to twenty
percent true value because of the
complexity of the how it's setup so a
tenet it is important to note that of
the oil and gas and many other things of
farming farming subsidies subsidies are
gigantic it is as I was like like when
somebody's like complaining about
subsidies why they're complaining about
what has the receives if we're like
number a hundred and fifty on the list
you have to really question their
motivations like if they're really about
subsidies what about the top 10 it's not
really about subsidies that that's
that's not really what they're attacking
so I get your extra stripper oil wells
get something like a 25-percent tax
credit
I don't know why we giving a 25 cent tax
credit destroy Wells is crazy i'm with
notamment by the way and then is the the
whole scam where all companies can do
zero-cost leases in foreign countries
and just pay taxes and then not pay
taxes in the US this is like one of the
biggest scams ever know Lisa's truly 0
value but if you if you'd give you if
you go is 0-2 very low value and lease
we pretend that you're getting Ted text
instead that you don't pay tax in the
u.s. so really giant subsidy but but I
are going back to what is he saying
we're going to go this is hearing
instruments something it pans out that
were able to do the solar roof or less
than a normal roof before you even take
into account the cost of like that with
the value of the electricity that
assuming that pans out
well subsidies are generally matter
yes yes that includes labor cost of the
roof yeah absolutely without the roofing
supply chain is incredibly inefficient
and it's been a long time since people
really looked at that was the last time
anyone here had a conversation about a
roof
I mean it's like we're so just hasn't
your roofing isn't going to look at is
just not got a lot not gotten a lot of
love you know so looking at this the
supply chain efficiency and going to a
high-strength glass instead of concrete
or ceramic tile the that the glass ways
maybe a third to a quarter
sometimes you have 50 as much as a
regular ceramic or concrete tile and
most of the cost of that the tiles is
actually transport logistics costs are
huge and they tend to quite fragile so
the in-process breakage of the ceramic
and concretize very high so a lot of
breakage very high transport costs the
density is not very good that would be
quite thick and and the whole supply
chain from where they're made to where
they're finally installed is is really
inefficient to display it kind of
cleaning that up there are huge gains
turns out they've been just one maybe
two more questions
sure
yeah the list to sell it uses a very
high efficiency cell will be using a
hybrid high-efficiency sell that that's
in the cell efficiency be in the you
know low to mid-twenties kind of 22 22
22 twenty-four percent efficient at the
cell level and then it's like laminated
to take it behind decorative glass high
tech high strength class and then you're
very clever about how you connect all
those cells together and what the
backplane looks like but honestly
looking at this it's like I don't know
why anyone is not doing its not that
crazy hard so it's me it's okay at the
back pressure i'm most concerned with
getting rid of the fossil fuel industry
PG&E forward slash solar choice for
three cents more per your kilowatt-hour
will give you whatever will give you
solar energy from solar farms in
Northern California keeps our economy in
California strong term and you can do it
today
alright sounds great so I mean I know
that maybe you want to put roofs on our
roof wouldn't take solar panels
well actually for even the even the roof
it's got too many tables and has trees
so everybody under which over it's just
if we get rid of the fossil fuel
industry then electric cars will and
SolarCity will do better
sure every what one last question
sure good
alright this is less about the subject
matter
yes it is
yeah it is i think actually the actual
sentence you get one's really lowering
their eyes is tiny so excluding that low
angle energy has very little effect
yeah and then hit the way the way that
the sort of that the microstructure of
the way it's arranged you can actually
get internal reflections so as the
photon comes instead of bouncing right
out it can actually bounce around inside
and and kick down an electron which is
you know politics so it turns out that
it actually that the benefit because it
would benefit offsets the efficiency had
to some degree it looks like it's
probably going to be close to even you
know make it flat plus my as a few
percent so I think you aren't picky